Guide to the Paul A. Samuelson papers, 1933-2010 and undated RL.10082
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Paul A. Samuelson papers
1933-2010 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Samuelson, Paul A. (Paul Anthony), 1915-2009
RL.10082
119 Linear Feet
Paul A. Samuelson was a Nobel Prize-winning economist and professor at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology. The Paul Samuelson papers span the years 1933 to 2010 and cover nearly all aspects of his long career. The collection is arranged in the following series: Audiovisual Materials, Awards, Committees and Projects, Correspondence, Printed Materials, Speeches and Interviews, Teaching Materials, and Unpublished Writings. Significant correspondents include Milton Friedman, Don Patinkin, and Robert Solow, and many other notable economists, Nobel prize winners, politicians, and scientists. Researchers will find materials representing Samuelson's work on diverse topics of economic theory, including the history of economic thought (post-Keynesian economics, neoclassical economics, and thinkers such as Marx, Sraffa and Ricardo), financial economics, growth theory, international finance, inflation, stability, welfare economics, post-World War economic policies and stabilization, stochastic analysis, utility, monetary policy, Marxist economics, biological economics - including population and gender studies, thermodynamics, and mathematical economics. Finally, the Samuelson Papers also document his strong contributions to the U.S. government, especially his work for the Federal Reserve, and to federally-funded projects, professional committees and boards, and organizations and societies, beginning in the 1940s and continuing throughout his career.
Approx. 88,950 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Electronic records in this collection have been migrated to a library server and digital use copies can only be accessed onsite in the Rubenstein Library Reading Room. To request access, please contact Research Services before coming to use these records.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Paul A. Samuelson papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2010 and 2011.
Biographical Note
Chronology
1915, May 15 Born in Gary, Indiana, son of Russian-born parents Frank Samuelson and Ella Lipton
1932 Graduated Hyde Park High School, Chicago
1935 B.A., University of Chicago
1935-1937 Social Science Research Council Pre-doctoral Fellow
1936 M.A., Harvard University
1937-1940 Society of Fellows, Harvard University
1940-1944 Assistant Professor of Economics, Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT)
1941 Ph.D. (David A. Wells Prize), Harvard University
1944-1947 Associate Professor of Economics, MIT
1947-1966 Professor of Economics, MIT
1948-1949 Guggenheim Fellow
1958-1959 Ford Faculty Research Fellow
1966-1986 Institute Professor, MIT
1970 Alfred Nobel Memorial Prize in Economic Science
1971 Albert Einstein Commemorative Award
1986-2009 Gordon Y. Billard Fellow, Institute Professor Emeritus, MIT
1990 Gold Scanno Prize in Economy, Naples, Italy
1991 MIT established Paul A. Samuelson Professorship in Economics
1996 Awarded National Medal of Science
2009, Dececember 13 Died, Belmont, Massachusetts
Collection Overview
The Paul A. Samuelson Papers span the years 1933 to 2010, and cover nearly all aspects of his long career. Materials are arranged in the original order maintained by Samuelson, and include his professional correspondence files; unpublished writings, notes, drafts and fragments; audiovisual materials; documents regarding awards, including the Nobel Prize; files relating to various grants, committees, and projects; teaching materials from his years at MIT; files of speeches; and publication files, including professional and mainstream media articles. Significant correspondents include Milton Friedman, Don Patinkin, and Robert Solow, as well as many other notable economists, Nobel prize winners, politicians, and scientists. Material can also be found on economic programs at institutions such as MIT, where Samuelson established a renowned economics faculty. Researchers will find materials representing Samuelson's work on diverse topics of economic theory, including the history of economic thought (post-Keynesian economics, neoclassical economics, and thinkers such as Marx, Sraffa and Ricardo), financial economics, growth theory, international finance, inflation, stability, welfare economics, post-World War economic policies and stabilization, stochastic analysis, utility, monetary policy, Marxist economics, biological economics - including population and gender studies, thermodynamics, and mathematical economics. Samuelson's insights on many of these subjects serve as organizational themes for large sections in the Unpublished Writings Series in the collection. Finally, the Samuelson Papers also document his strong contributions to the U.S. government, especially his work for the Federal Reserve, and to federally-funded projects, professional committees and boards, and organizations and societies, beginning in the 1940s and continuing throughout his career.
The Correspondence Series spans Samuelson's entire career, beginning in the 1930s. It consists mainly of professional exchanges with his colleagues in the U.S. and other countries. There are also files of correspondence with a wide variety of political and academic figures, presses, and media organizations. There is frequent correspondence with President Kennedy, for whom he was an economic advisor. Besides the named folders that represent notable economists such as Milton Friedman, John Kenneth Galbraith, Franco Modigliani, Don Patinkin, and Robert Solow, there are general correspondence folders in which a variety of documents are chronologically arranged. There is also a large group of files relating to the publication of his textbooks. Additional correspondence can be found in almost all the other series. A more detailed documentation of the Correspondence Series and its correspondents can be found in the series description.
A large series of Unpublished Writings contains many folders of unpublished articles, extensive research notes, jotted-down insights, and other fragmentary writings. The earliest pieces appear to be a typescript of Samuelson's 1933 diary and writings on collective bargaining (1933-1934). The wide range of topics in economic theory as well as the history of economics reflects Samuelson's interests over many decades, beginning with his work on Marx and the Transformation Problem, and later on, focusing more specifically on financial economics. The unpublished writings also reveal that he also wrote extensively on population and gender studies, thermodynamics, and mathematics.
The equally large Printed Materials Series houses a nearly complete collection of Samuelson's published articles in addition to a few of his monographs. In some cases, article folders include extensive correspondence between Samuelson and his editors and publishers. There is a complete list of Samuelson's publications available to researchers in the library, but not every publication listed is present in the collection. Located in this series is a copy of the thesis that Samuelson wrote while he was at Harvard, which in 1947 was published as the well-known Foundations of Economic Analysis. Also present in this series are the many columns and articles he wrote for Newsweek in the 1960s and 1970s.
Other aspects of Samuelson's career can be found in course files which form the Teaching Materials Series, most of which contain reading lists and syllabi, and in the Committees and Projects Series, which contains information on his many consultancy roles, grant-funded projects, and professional service. Examples include projects for the Radiation Laboratory and the Rand Corporation, and contributions to government agencies such as the U.S. War Production Board and the Federal Reserve Board, as well as academic organizations such as the National Science Foundation, the National Academy of Science and the Econometric Society.
The smallest series of the collection, the Awards Series contains materials relating to Samuelson's Nobel Prize in Economics in 1970 and his Medal of Science award in 1996. Files contain congratulatory letters and telegrams, and his outgoing correspondence to subsequent Nobel Prize winners. In contrast to this small series, the large Speeches and Interviews Series houses paper drafts or transcripts of nearly all of Samuelson's public presentations, amounting to over 400 lectures, speeches, and interviews. Some of these can also be found on recorded media in the Audiovisual Series.
The Audiovisual Materials Series features 320 cassettes from the commercially produced Economics Cassettes Series, a set of interviews with Milton Friedman and Paul Samuelson on economics issues of the times. There are also a few tapes and cassettes of lectures and speeches by Samuelson. Items related to the topics and events represented in this series are also found in the Teaching Materials, Speeches and Interviews, and Awards Series. There is a DVD recording of the 2010 MIT memorial service which provides many images of Samuelson taken throughout his life, filling in for the absence of photographs in the collection. Original audiovisual materials are closed to use; listening or viewing copies may need to be made by staff for access. Please contact Research Services before coming to use this series.
Collection Arrangement
Organized into the following series: Audiovisual Material, Awards, Committees and Projects, Correspondence, Printed Material, Speeches and Interviews, Teaching Material, and Unpublished Writings.
Conditions Governing Access note
[Original audiovisual materials are closed to use. Use of these materials may require production of listening or viewing copies. Please contact Research Services before coming to use this collection.]
Related Material
The David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library at Duke University also holds many of Samuelson's printed materials and textbooks.
Economists' Papers Project (Many of the economists present in Samuelson's papers have deposited their own professional papers in the library: these include Arrow, Bronfenbrenner, Burns, Domar, Georgescu-Roegen, Metzler, Modigliani, Morgernstern, Patinkin, Perlman, and Solow, and S. Weintraub.)
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Milton Friedman Economics Cassette Series
Hoover Institution, Stanford University
Monetary policy -- Econometric models; Economic history; Economic stabilization; Economics -- History -- 20th century; Economics, Mathematical; Economists -- Correspondence; Economists -- Methodology; Economists -- United States; Welfare economics; Stochastic analysis; Nobel Prize winners; Neoclassical school of economics; Public goods -- Econometric models; Post-Keynesian economics; Neoclassical school of economics -- History; Monetary policy -- United States; United States -- Economic policy; World War, 1939-1945 -- Economic aspects; United States -- Economic conditions -- 1945-; Audiovisual materials; Clippings (information artifacts); Video recordings; International finance; Inflation -- Econometric models; Human biology -- Economic aspects; Economics -- Study and teaching (Higher); DVDs; Audiocassettes; Marxian economics; Friedman, Milton, 1912-2006; Board of Governors of the Federal Reserve System (U.S.); Massachusetts Institute of Technology. Dept. of Economics; Marx, Karl, 1818-1883; Ricardo, David, 1772-1823; Patinkin, Don; Samuelson, Paul A. (Paul Anthony), 1915-2009; Sraffa, Piero; Solow, Robert M.
- Audiovisual Materials, 1960-2009
  Conditions Governing Access Note
  Original audiovisual materials are closed to use. Use of these materials may require production of listening or viewing copies. Please contact Research Services before coming to use this Series.
  Scope and Contents
  Chiefly made up of two sets of the Economics Cassette Series produced by Instructional Dynamics Incorporated (IDI) between 1968 and 1977, the Audiovisual Materials Series contains 191 cassette tape recordings featuring interviews with Paul Samuelson and 125 cassettes featuring interviews with Milton Friedman, discussing fiscal policy and other issues through their respective lenses of Keynesian and Monetarist economics. Many of the Friedman interviews listed here have been digitized by the Hoover Institution at Stanford and may be accessed online through its website on Friedman: http://hoohila.stanford.edu/friedman/ecs.php.
  The series also includes open reel audio of two of Samuelson's lectures, a video response to a 1975 video lecture by Samuelson from a group of German students at the University of Cologne, and a film reel of Samuelson winning the Nobel Prize.
  - Economics Cassette Series: Paul Samuelson, 1969-1977; 1
    - Tape 1 - untitled, circa 1969 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0001)
    - Tape 2 - untitled, circa 1969 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0002)
    - Tape 3 - untitled, circa 1969 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0003)
    - Tape 4 - untitled, circa 1969 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0004)
    - Tape 5 - untitled, circa 1969 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0005)
    - Tape 6 - untitled, 1969 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0006)
    - Tape 7 - untitled, 1969 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0007)
    - Tape 8 - untitled, 1969 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0008)
    - Tape 9 - Year end review; continuation of 1969 forecast (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0009)
    - Tape 10 - Interest rates; more 1969 forecast (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0010)
    - Tape 11 - Difference of opinion between Samuelson and Friedman, 1969 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0011)
    - Tape 12 - President's economic report, 1969 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0012)
    - Tape 13 - Current information; analysis of our economic destiny this year and future, 1969 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0013)
    - Tape 14 - New economics conference board forecast, 1969 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0014)
    - Tape 15 - General direction of economic activity, 1969 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0015)
    - Tape 16 - Prime rate; stock market-Nixon; tax reform, 1969 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0016)
    - Tape 17 - Views of 1969; FRB report; D-J adjustments (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0017)
    - Tape 18 - Federal reserve forecast, 1969 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0018)
    - Tape 19 - International gold situation, 1969 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0019)
    - Tape 20 - General topics, 1969 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0020)
    - Tape 21 - Review of first quarter 1969 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0021)
    - Tape 22 - Eisenhower, 1969 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0022)
    - Tape 23 - Stock market, 1969 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0023)
    - Tape 24 - Response to subscribers, 1969 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0024)
    - Tape 25 - First quarter review, 1969 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0025)
    - Tape 26 - Nixon's first 100 days, 1969 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0026)
    - Tape 27 - Basic economics, 1969 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0027)
    - Tape 28 - Subscribers' questions, 1969 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0028)
    - Tape 29 - Summary of recent events; subscribers' questions, 1969 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0029)
    - Tape 30 - America's balance of payments; stock market, 1969 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0030)
    - Tape 31 - First half of 1969 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0031)
    - Tape 32 - Inflation, circa 1969 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0032)
    - Tape 33 - GNP; surtax, circa 1969 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0033)
    - Tape 34 - Samuelson vs. Friedman, circa 1969 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0034)
    - Tape 35 - Economics' credibility; forecast for 4th quarter, circa 1969 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0035)
    - Tape 36 - Business outlook, circa 1969 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0036)
    - Tape 37 - International situation, circa 1969 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0037)
    - Tape 38 - Review of 3rd quarter GNP, circa 1969 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0038)
    - Tape 39 - Comments on some 1970 forecasts, circa 1969 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0039)
    - Tape 40 - Subscribers questions; nobel peace prize winners, circa 1969 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0040)
    - Tape 41 - Inflation; youth and economics, circa 1969 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0041)
    - Tape 42 - 1970 forecast, circa 1969 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0042)
    - Tape 43 - State of the union, circa 1969 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0043)
    - Tape 44 - Economic growth in 1970, circa 1970 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0044)
    - Tape 45 - untitled, circa 1970 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0045)
    - Tape 46 - Revision of 1970 economic forecasts, circa 1970 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0046)
    - Tape 47 - Black America and the economy, circa 1970 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0047)
    - Tape 48 - Mid-recession ends, circa 1970 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0048)
    - Tape 49 - The stock market and college investment profolios, circa 1970 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0049)
    - Tape 50 - The Wall Street situation, circa 1970 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0050)
    - Tape 51 - Another look at Wall Street, circa 1970 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0051)
    - Tape 52 - Answers to subscribers; inquiries; revised forecast, circa 1970 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0052)
    - Tape 53 - An economic look at 1970, circa 1970-1971 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0053)
    - Tape 54 - Economic outlook for 1971, circa 1970-1971 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0054)
    - Tape 55 - Statistical revisions- a fair prediction, circa 1970-1971 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0055)
    - Tape 56 - Income policies, circa 1970-1971 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0056)
    - Tape 57 - Forecasting the future: ten year economic outlooks, circa 1970-1971 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0057)
    - Tape 58 - Economic retardation ends, circa 1970-1971 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0058)
    - Tape 59 - The world wide money situation, circa 1970-1971 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0059)
    - Tape 60 - Comments on some 1971 economic forecasts, circa 1970-1971 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0060)
    - Tape 61 - untitled, circa 1970-1971 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0061)
    - Tape 62 - How strikes effect GNP, circa 1970-1971 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0062)
    - Tape 63 - Effect of GM strike on fourth quarter GNP, circa 1970-1971 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0063)
    - Tape 64 - Federal reserve: controlling the money supply, circa 1970-1971 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0064)
    - Tape 65 - Fixed rate of growth for money supply, circa 1970-1971 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0065)
    - Tape 66 - The US economy: 1970 what's ahead for 1971, circa 1970-1971 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0066)
    - Tape 67 - The president and the economy, circa 1970-1971 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0067)
    - Tape 68 - Will automatic wage controls work, circa 1970-1971 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0068)
    - Tape 69 - 1971: there's good news tonight, circa 1970-1971 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0069)
    - Tape 70 - Why are they laughing at Laffer, circa 1970-1971 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0070)
    - Tape 71 - Systematic divergences between broad and narrow money supplies, circa 1970-1971 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0071)
    - Tape 72 - Reviewing 1971's first quarter: a preview, circa 1970-1971 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0072)
    - Tape 73 - Grounding the SST an economic argument, circa 1970-1971 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0073)
    - Tape 74 - 1971: official first quarter analysis, circa 1970-1971 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0074)
    - Tape 75 - Economic expansion: how fast, circa 1970-1971 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0075)
    - Tape 76 - The European monetary crisis, circa 1970-1971 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0076)
    - Tape 77 - Are political beliefs and economic forecasts related, 1971 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0077)
    - Tape 78 - The future of the affluent state, 1971 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0078)
    - Tape 79 - Previews of 4th quarter effects of possible steel strike, 1971 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0079)
    - Tape 80 - Administration naming of policy makers; effects of jobless figures on SNP, 1971 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0080)
    - Tape 81 - Declining US balance of trade, 1971 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0081)
    - Tape 82 - Pessimism in the economy, 1971 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0082)
    - Tape 83 - Effects on president's economic policy changes, circa 1971 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0083)
    - Tape 84 - Foreign reaction to American dollar evaluation, 1971 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0084)
    - Tape 85 - Computer-base economic forecasts, circa 1971 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0085)
    - Tape 86 - European viewpoint of Nixon economic policies, 1971 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0086)
    - Tape 87 - The martin report on the New York Stock Exchange, 1971 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0087)
    - Tape 88 - Review of 1971 3rd quarter statistics (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0088)
    - Tape 89 - Economic component's effect on 1972, 1971 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0089)
    - Tape 90 - Economic outlook for 1972, 1971 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0090)
    - Tape 91 - Meaning of the McCracken resignation; international money situation, 1971 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0091)
    - Tape 93 - The economics of the stock market, 1972 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0092)
    - Tape 94 - The international monetary situation, 1972 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0093)
    - Tape 96 - Value added tax, 1972 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0094)
    - Tape 97 - Dollar parity in the current market, 1972 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0095)
    - Tape 98 - Everything you always wanted to know about current economics, 1972 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0096)
    - Tape 99 - The economics of zero population growth, 1972 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0097)
    - Tape 100 - 1972 first quarter figures (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0098)
    - Tape 101 - International trade for a rich country, 1972 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0099)
    - Tape 102 - Change in the treasury department, 1972 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0100)
    - Tape 103 - International trade for a rich country part II, 1972 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0101)
    - Tape 104 - Senator McGovern's politics, 1972 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0102)
    - Tape 105 - The British pound, 1972 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0103)
    - Tape 106 - Mid-year: preview 1972-73 forecasts (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0104)
    - Tape 107 - The American economy mid-year 1972 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0105)
    - Tape 108 - Balance of payments: one year later, 1972 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0106)
    - Tape 109 - The American economy, after Nixon's re-election, 1972 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0107)
    - Tape 110 - The new McGovern economics program, 1972 (Box 1, Audio-cassette RL10082-CS-0108)